is not sure what a coral is or where they come from. How would we get someone to care about the world's coral reefs when it's an abstract thing they can barely understand? If they don't understand what a coral is or where it comes from, or how funny or interesting or beautiful it is, why would we expect them to care about saving them? So let's change that. What is a coral and where does it come from? Corals are born in a number of different ways, but most often by mass spawning: all of the individuals of a single species on one night a year, releasing all the eggs they've made that year into the water column, packaged into bundles with sperm cells. And those bundles go to the surface of the ocean and break apart. And hopefully -- hopefully -- at the surface of the ocean, they meet the eggs and sperm from other corals. And that is why you need lots of corals on a coral reef -- so that all of their eggs can meet their match at the surface. When they're fertilized, they do what any other animal egg does: divides in half again and again and again. Taking these photos under the microscope every year is one of my favorite and most magical moments of the year. At the end of all this cell division, they turn into a swimming larva -- a little tiny blob of fat the size of a poppy seed, but with all of the sensory systems that we have. They can sense color and light, textures, chemicals, pH. They can even feel pressure waves; they can hear sound. And they use those talents to search the bottom of the reef for a place to attach and live the rest of their lives. So imagine finding a place where you would live the rest of your life when you were just two days old. They attach in the place they find most suitable, they build a skeleton underneath themselves, they build a mouth and tentacles, and then they begin the difficult work of building the world's coral reefs. One coral polyp will divide itself again and again and again, leaving a limestone skeleton underneath itself and growing up toward the sun. Given hundreds of years and many species, what you get is a massive limestone structure that can be seen from space in many cases, covered by a thin skin of these hardworking animals. Now, there are only a few hundred species of corals on the planet, maybe 1,000. But these systems house millions and millions of other species, and that diversity is what stabilizes the systems, and it's where we're finding our new medicines. It's how we find new sources of food. I'm lucky enough to work on the island of Curaçao, where we still have reefs that look like this. But, indeed, much of the Caribbean and much of our world is much more like this. Scientists have studied in increasing detail the loss of the world's coral reefs, and they have documented with increasing certainty the causes. But in my research, I'm not interested in looking backward. My colleagues and I in Curaçao are interested in looking forward at what might be. And we have the tiniest reason to be optimistic. Because even in some of these reefs that we probably could have written off long ago, we sometimes see baby corals arrive and survive anyway. And we're starting to think that baby corals may have the ability to adjust to some of the conditions that the adults couldn't. They may be able to adjust ever so slightly more readily to this human planet. So in the research I do with my colleagues in Curaçao, we try to figure out what a baby coral needs in that critical early stage, what it's looking for and how we can try to help it through that process. I'm going to show you three examples of the work we've done to try to answer those questions. A few years ago we took a 3D printer and we made coral choice surveys -- different colors and different textures, and we simply asked the coral where they preferred to settle. And we found that corals, even without the biology involved, still prefer white and pink, the colors of a healthy reef. And they prefer crevices and grooves and holes, where they will be safe from being trampled or eaten by a predator. So we can use this knowledge, we can go back and say we need to restore those factors -- that pink, that white, those crevices, those hard surfaces -- in our conservation projects. We can also use that knowledge if we're going to put something underwater, like a sea wall or a pier. We can choose to use the materials and colors and textures that might bias the system back toward those corals. Now in addition to the surfaces, we also study the chemical and microbial signals that attract corals to reefs. Starting about six years ago, I began culturing bacteria from surfaces where corals had settled. And I tried those one by one by one, looking for the bacteria that would convince corals to settle and attach. And we now have many bacterial strains in our freezer that will reliably cause corals to go through that settlement and attachment process. So as we speak, my colleagues in Curaçao are testing those bacteria to see if they'll help us raise more coral settlers in the lab, and to see if those coral settlers will survive better when we put them back underwater. Now in addition to these tools, we also try to uncover the mysteries of species that are under-studied. This is one of my favorite corals, and always has been: dendrogyra cylindrus, the pillar coral. I love it because it makes this ridiculous shape, because its tentacles are fat and look fuzzy and because it's rare. Finding one of these on a reef is a treat. In fact, it's so rare, that last year it was listed as a threatened species on the endangered species list. And this was in part because in over 30 years of research surveys, scientists had never found a baby pillar coral. We weren't even sure if they could still reproduce, or if they were still reproducing. So four years ago, we started following these at night and watching to see if we could figure out when they spawn in Curaçao. We got some good tips from our colleagues in Florida, who had seen one in 2007, one in 2008, and eventually we figured out when they spawn in Curaçao and we caught it. Here's a female on the left with some eggs in her tissue, about to release them into the seawater. And here's a male on the right, releasing sperm. We collected this, we got it back to the lab, we got it to fertilize and we got baby pillar corals swimming in our lab. Thanks to the work of our scientific aunts and uncles, and thanks to the 10 years of practice we've had in Curaçao at raising other coral species, we got some of those larvae to go through the rest of the process and settle and attach, and turn into metamorphosed corals. So this is the first pillar coral baby that anyone ever saw. (Applause) And I have to say -- if you think baby pandas are cute, this is cuter. (Laughter) So we're starting to figure out the secrets to this process, the secrets of coral reproduction and how we might help them. And this is true all around the world; scientists are figuring out new ways to handle their embryos, to get them to settle, maybe even figuring out the methods to preserve them at low temperatures, so that we can preserve their genetic diversity and work with them more often. But this is still so low-tech. We are limited by the space on our bench, the number of hands in the lab and the number of coffees we can drink in any given hour. Now, compare that to our other crises and our other areas of concern as a society. We have advanced medical technology, we have defense technology, we have scientific technology, we even have advanced technology for art. But our technology for conservation is behind. Think back to the most difficult job you ever did. Many of you would say it was being a parent. My mother described being a parent as something that makes your life far more amazing and far more difficult than you could've ever possibly imagined. I've been trying to help corals become parents for over 10 years now. And watching the wonder of life has certainly filled me with amazement to the core of my soul. But I've also seen how difficult it is for them to become parents. The pillar corals spawned again two weeks ago, and we collected their eggs and brought them back to the lab. And here you see one embryo dividing, alongside 14 eggs that didn't fertilize and will blow up. They'll be infected with bacteria, they will explode and those bacteria will threaten the life of this one embryo that has a chance. We don't know if it was our handling methods that went wrong and we don't know if it was just this coral on this reef, always suffering from low fertility. Whatever the cause, we have much more work to do before we can use baby corals to grow or fix or, yes, maybe save coral reefs. So never mind that they're worth hundreds of billions of dollars. Coral reefs are hardworking animals and plants and microbes and fungi. They're providing us with art and food and medicine. And we almost took out an entire generation of corals. But a few made it anyway, despite our best efforts, and now it's time for us to thank them for the work they did and give them every chance they have to raise the coral reefs of the future, their coral babies. Thank you so much. (Applause)
peu savent ce que sont les coraux et d'où ils viennent. Comment amener quelqu'un à se soucier des coraux quand ce n'est qu'une abstraction qu'il comprend à peine. S'il ne comprend ni leur nature, ni leur origine, ni à quel point ils sont curieux, intéressants, beaux, comment s'attendre à ce qu'il les protège ? Alors changeons cela. Qu'est-ce qu'un corail ? D'où vient-il ? Les coraux naissent de différentes façons, mais souvent par fraie en masse de tous les individus d'une espèce une nuit par an. Ils libèrent tous les œufs de l'année dans la colonne d'eau, empaquetés de spermatozoïdes. Ces paquets remontent à la surface et se défont. Et là, on espère très fort qu'ils croisent œufs et sperme d'autres coraux. Donc il faut beaucoup de coraux dans un récif pour que tous les œufs trouvent un partenaire. Quand ils sont fécondés, ils font comme tous les œufs : ils se divisent encore et encore. Faire ces photos au microscope chaque année est un moment magique, un de mes préférés. A la fin de cette division ils se transforment en larves, de minuscules gouttes de graisse, grosses comme des grains de pavot mais qui ont le même système sensoriel que nous, percevant couleurs, lumière, textures, produits chimiques, pH. Ils sentent la pression des vagues, entendent les sons. Et ils utilisent ces talents pour chercher au bas du récif un endroit où s'accrocher et passer le reste de leur vie. Imaginez donc trouver un lieu pour y passer votre vie quand vous n'aviez que 2 jours. Ils choisissent l'endroit qui leur paraît le meilleur, ils construisent un squelette sous eux, puis une bouche, des tentacules, puis le plus difficile : les récifs coralliens. Un polype corallien se divise laissant sous lui un squelette de calcaire. Il croît en direction du soleil. Après des centaines d'années et beaucoup d'espèces, vous avez une énorme structure calcaire souvent visible de l'espace, couverte par une fine couche de ces animaux travailleurs. Ce ne sont que quelques centaines d'espèces, peut-être 1 000, mais elles abritent des millions d'autres espèces, et cette diversité stabilise le système. C'est là qu'on trouve nos nouveaux médicaments, de nouvelles sources de nourriture. J'ai la chance de travailler sur l'île de Curaçao, où nous avons encore des récifs comme ceci. mais la plus grande part des Caraïbes et du monde est bien plus comme cela. Les scientifiques ont étudié en détail la perte en récifs dans le monde, ils en ont montré les causes de plus en plus certaines. Mais dans mes recherches, le passé ne m'intéresse pas. Avec mes collègues on s'intéresse au futur, à ce qui pourrait être. Et nous avons une infime raison d'être optimiste. Car même dans certains récifs qu'on aurait pu rayer de la carte il y a longtemps, on voit parfois des bébés arriver, et survivre malgré tout. On pense qu'ils ont la capacité de s'adapter à des conditions invivables pour les adultes. Ils peuvent peut-être s'adapter un peu mieux à cette planète humaine. Donc dans nos recherches à Curaçao, on essaie de déterminer les besoins d'un bébé corail à ce moment critique, ce qu'il cherche, et comment l'aider. Voici 3 exemples de ce qu'on a fait pour essayer de répondre à ces questions. Avec une imprimante 3D, on a créé des enquêtes sur le choix des coraux, avec différentes couleurs et textures, et on a demandé aux coraux où ils préféraient s'installer. On a vu que les coraux, en dehors de toute biologie, préfèrent le blanc et le rose, couleurs d'un récif sain. Ils préfèrent les crevasses, rainures et trous, où ils ne risquent pas d'être piétinés ou mangés par un prédateur. On peut utiliser ce savoir pour dire qu'il faut restaurer ce rose et blanc, ces crevasses, et surfaces dures dans nos projets de conservation. On peut utiliser ce savoir si on veut construire sous l'eau une digue ou une jetée. On peut choisir des matériaux, des couleurs et des textures qui pourraient être favorables aux coraux. En plus des surfaces, on étudie les signaux chimiques et microbiens qui attirent les coraux vers les récifs. Il y a 6 ans j'ai commencé à cultiver des bactéries prises où des coraux s'étaient installés. Je les ai testées une par une, cherchant celle qui convaincrait les coraux de s'installer. On a maintenant des souches bactériennes congelées pouvant permettre à des coraux d'accomplir ce processus d'installation et de fixation. Donc en ce moment, mes collègues sont en train de tester ces bactéries pour voir si elles vont permettre d'obtenir plus de colonisateurs, et s'ils survivront mieux quand on les remettra à l'eau. De plus on essaie de percer les mystères d'espèces peu étudiées. Voici un de mes coraux préférés, depuis toujours : cylindrus dendrogyra, les cierges de la mer. J'aime leurs drôles de formes, leurs tentacules grassouillets et duveteux, et parce qu'ils sont rares. En trouver est une chance. En fait c'est si rare que depuis l'an dernier, ils sont espèce menacée dans la liste des espèces en danger, en partie parce que en plus de 30 ans de relevés, les scientifiques n'ont jamais vu de bébé de ce corail. On n'était même pas sûr qu'ils puissent encore se reproduire. Donc il y a 4 ans, on s'est mis à les suivre la nuit pour essayer de voir quand ils frayent à Curaçao. On a eu de bons conseils de nos collègues de Floride, qui en avaient vu en 2007 et 2008, et on a pu déterminer quand le frai a lieu chez nous et y assister. Voici une femelle à gauche, qui porte des œufs, prête à les libérer dans l'eau. Voici un mâle à droite, lâchant du sperme. On a tout récupéré, fait la fécondation au labo et on a eu des bébés nageurs de cierges de la mer au labo. Grâce au travail de nos prédécesseurs, et à nos 10 ans de pratique dans l'élevage d'autres coraux, on a obtenu que des larves aillent au bout du processus, s'installent, se fixent et deviennent des coraux. Voici donc le premier bébé cierge de mer jamais vu. (Applaudissements) Si, pour vous, les bébés pandas sont mignons, pour moi, ça, c'est plus mignon. (Rires) Donc on commence à comprendre les secrets de la reproduction des coraux et comment les aider. C'est vrai pour le monde entier : on trouve de nouvelles façons de manipuler les embryons pour qu'ils s'installent et peut-être même des méthodes pour les conserver à basse température et ainsi pouvoir préserver leur diversité génétique et travailler avec eux plus souvent. Mais c'est très rudimentaire. On est limité en espace, en personnel, en nombre de cafés qu'on peut boire à l'heure. Comparez à d'autres crises, d'autres préoccupations de la société. On a des technologies de pointe dans le médical, la défense, la science, et même l'art. Mais pour l'écologie, on est en retard. Pensez au travail le plus difficile que vous ayez fait. Beaucoup diraient « être parent ». Ma mère a dit qu'être parent rendait la vie bien plus étonnante et bien plus difficile qu'on aurait pu l'imaginer. J'essaie d'aider les coraux à devenir parents depuis plus de 10 ans. Observer les merveilles du vivant m'a certainement remplie d'étonnement au plus profond de mon âme. Mais j'ai vu comme il leur est difficile de devenir parents. Les cierges ont encore frayé il y a 15 jours, on a récupéré leurs œufs pour le labo. Là vous voyez un embryon se diviser à côté de 14 œufs non fécondés qui éclateront. Infectés par des bactéries, ils exploseront, et ces bactéries menaceront la vie de cet unique embryon qui a une chance de vivre. On ne sait pas si c'est une erreur de manipulation, on ne sait pas si le corail de ce récif-là souffre toujours d'une faible fertilité. Quelle que soit la cause, on a beaucoup de travail avant d'obtenir que des bébés coraux grandissent, se fixent, ou peut-être, sauvent les récifs. Alors peu importe qu'ils vaillent des centaines de millions, les récifs, à la fois animaux, végétaux, microbes, champignons, travaillent dur. Ils produisent de l'art, de la nourriture des médicaments. On a presque anéanti toute une génération de coraux. Mais quelques-uns ont survécu malgré toutes nos actions, et maintenant il est temps de les remercier pour leur travail et de leur donner toutes leurs chances pour élever les récifs du futur : leurs bébés coraux. Merci beaucoup ! (Applaudissements)